Guide to the Jefferson Cleveland Grinnalds papers, 1908-1966, 1920-1960 (bulk)
Grinnalds, Jefferson Cleveland papers, 1908-1966, 1920-1960 (bulk)
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Jefferson Cleveland Grinnalds papers, 1908-1966 1920-1960
2617
Jefferson Cleveland Grinnalds, 1884-1966.
10 cubic ft.
Correspondence, monographs, reports, articles, plans, and maps.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection includes correspondence (1920-1966) with planners, clients, and professional groups; zoning ordinances and plans for Baltimore, Frederick, Salisbury, Annapolis, and Bel Air, Maryland; Raleigh and Burlington, North Carolina; and Martinsburg, West Virginia; monographs and reports by Grinnalds and other planners including Edward M. Bassett and Robert Whitten; selected magazine articles on zoning (1922-1934); plans and maps for towns and cities particularly in Maryland; and newspaper clippings on zoning.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Jefferson Cleveland Grinnalds was a city planner and zoning expert.
Some educational and professional qualifications and experiences:
Studied engineering at the University of Virginia.
Studied law at the University of Maryland.
Graduate work at Johns Hopkins University In history of art, architecture, Greek and Roman archaeology, biblical archaeology, Greek, Roman, Egyptian, Assyrian and Babylonian history - all for ancient town planning.
Port Development and Sociology at the University of Maryland.
Taught City Planning and City Planning Practice at Johns Hopkins University.
Lectured on Zoning at Goucher College Johns Hopkins, University of Maryland and University of Virginia.
Directed surveys, designed the plan and wrote first zoning ordinance for Baltimore City.
The same services for Baltimore's second Zoning ordinance not in effect.
City Planning Expert appointed by Mr. Herbert Hoover on staff of commission to design a model state zoning enabling act, also a model planning act
Both acts adopted by almost all states in United States including Maryland.
Consultant to Raleigh, Burlington and Rooky Mount, North Carolina.
Prepared plans and zoning ordinances for all these cities.
Zoned Raleigh completely the second time twenty-one years after the first.
Consultant to Annapolis, Frederick, Hagerstown, Cumberland, Salisbury and Bel Air, Maryland.
Prepared plans and zoning ordinances for all these cities.
Zoned Frederick and Salisbury twice.
Master plans for Bel Air, Frederick and Martinsburg, West Virginia.
Airport zoning ordinance for Frederick.
Zoning for about thirty-five square miles of Berkeley County, West Virginia,
Zoning for Seaford, Delaware and Consultant on street plan.
Consultant on annual retainer for two days monthly for Planning Commission and also for Board of Zoning Adjustment - for Martinsburg, West Virginia, at present and for past four years.
Author of many published articles on city planning and zoning.
Author of many briefs and reports on same subject matter.
Expert witness many times in trial cases on same subjects.
Secretary - Engineer of three Zoning Commissions of Baltimore City.
Secretary - Engineer and Zoning Administrator of Board of Zoning Appeals, Baltimore.
Recent report on Roscoe G. Rowe.
Boulevard in Annapolis for Planning Advisory Committee.
Other Annapolis when called by the City.
Engineering experience included surveying, topographic maps, street planning, property subdivision, railroads, steel and concrete bridges, street and road paving, mining, machine design, machine shop management, oil and gas field engineering, steel building construction, consulting engineer.
Practiced zoning and planning solely for last thirty years.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection includes correspondence (1920-1966) with planners, clients, and professional groups; zoning ordinances and plans for Baltimore, Frederick, Salisbury, Annapolis, and Bel Air, Maryland; Raleigh and Burlington, North Carolina; and Martinsburg, West Virginia; monographs and reports by Grinnalds and other planners including Edward M. Bassett and Robert Whitten; selected magazine articles on zoning (1922-1934); plans and maps for towns and cities particularly in Maryland; and newspaper clippings on zoning. Major correspondents are Edward M. Bassett, Thomas Eldridge, P. C. Painter, and Gustav Jaeger Requardt. Also, occasional letters from Harland Bartholomew, Alfred Bettman, Russell Van Nest Black, Arthur Comey, and mayors of cities retaining Grinnalds as a consultant; and one letter from Herbert Hoover concerning Grinnalds' zoning ordinance for Baltimore.
CORRESPONDENTS (with number of letters)
Bahlke, George W. (N.Y.C.)
4
Bassett, Edward M.
42
Bonnell, Robert O. (National Economy League)
4
Broening, William F. (Mayor of Baltimore)
1
Brown, Charles Carroll (American Society for Municipal Improvements)
9
Brown, W. Lesley (City Manager, Tampa, Fla.)
1
Buttenheim, Harold S. (ed. of The American City)
1
Carmine, Mildred C. (Va.)
43
Clemens, M.A. (U. of Md.)
5
Clohan, Sarah Belle (Martinsburg, W. Va.)
31
Gofer, John I. (St. Louis, Mo.)
8
Coldren, Fred G. (B.C.)
6
Comey, Arthur C. (Mass)
Culbreth, E.E. (Mayor of Raleigh, N.C.)
2
Culler, Lloyd C. (Mayor of Frederick, Md.)
2
Dodds, H. W. (National Municipal League)
6
Eldridge, Thomas B. (Mayor of Raleigh, N.C.)
41
Ellicott, William M.
10
Faucette, W.D. (Seaboard Air Line Railway Corp., Norfolk)
3
Finch, Thomas A. (Mayor of Thomasville, N.C.)
3
France, Joseph Irwin (Md. Senator)
1
Gaither, Charles D. (Baltimore Police Commissioner)
1
Goldsborough, T. Alan (Md. Representative)
1
Goodman, Albert J. (Annapolis lawyer)
11
Gries, John M. (Dep't. of Commerce)
3
Madden, S.C. (ed. Municipal & County Engineering)
6
Hehl, Charles L. (Baltimore Rotary)
4
Hendren, W.H. Jr. (U. Va. Journal of Engineering)
3
Heydecker, Wayne D. (assoc. ed. The American City)
4
Hill, John Philip (Representative from Md.)
1
Hollis, Eleanor (Martinsburg, W. Va.)
87
Hoover, Herbert
1
Hubbard, Henry Vincent (Olmstead Brothers)
1
Hungerford, Arthur E. (Baltimore)
4
Hutzler, Jones B. (Mayor of Martinsburg, W. Va.)
3
Jackson, Howard W. (Mayor of Baltimore)
3
Kennedy, William (Parkersburg, W. Va.)
5
Kouwenhoven, William B. (Johns Hopkins U.)
1
Leavitt, Charles Wellford (N.Y.C.)
8
linthicum, J. Charles (Rep. from Md.)
1
McFarland, J. Horace (pres. American Civic Association)
1
McLendon, Ernest L. (Salisbury, Md.)
4
Martien, James Carey (Baltimore)
4
Mathias, Charles McC. (Frederick, Md.)
1
Mathias, Joseph L. (Westminster, Md.)
1
Moss, R. Maurice (Baltimore Urban League)
1
Mudd, Sydney E. (Rep. fromMd.)
1
Odum, Howard (U. of North Carolina)
3
O'Gorman, William J. (N.Y.C.)
1
Painter, P.O. (City Manager, Greensboro, North Carolina)
19
Perlman, Philip B. (Md. Secretary of State)
3
Pickens, Mrs. Robert (Vinton L.) (V.C.P.A.)
10
Ravenel, Bruce Walter (Walker, Ravenel, & Co., Columbia, S.C.)
6
Reguardt, Gustav Jaeger ('09) (Baltimore)
5
Rigsby, Rodford (City Manager, Greensboro, N.C.)
4
Ritchie, Albert (Sov. of Md.)
1
Saville, Alien J. (Richmond, Va.)
4
Shurtleff, Flavel
1
Spencer, John 0. (Morgan College, Baltimore)
1
Stewart, A. C. (Morgantown, W.Va.)
4
Takata, K. (Yokahama, Japan)
1
Taylor, James S. (Dept. of Commerce)
2
Thorn, Decourcy W.
3
Walker, Emily H. (Pinehurst, N.C.)
10
Wall, Perry G. (Mayor of Tampa, Fla.)
1
Walter, W.R. (Frederick)
8
Warren, Robert (assoc. ed. of The American City)
3
Weller, Ovington E. (Sen. from Md.)
1
Whitten, Robert
10
Willard, Daniel (B. & 0. R.R. president)
1
Zihlman, Frederick N. (Rep. from Md.)
1
Zug, George B. (Dartmouth College)
2
SUBJECTS
Names:
Grinnalds, Jefferson Cleveland, 1884-1966.; Bartholomew, Harland.; Bassett, Edward M. (Edward Murray), 1863-1948.; Bettman, Alfred, 1873-1945.; Black, Russell Van Nest, 1893-1969.; Comey, Arthur.; Eldridge, Thomas.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Painter, P. C.; Requardt, Gustav Jaeger.; Whitten, Robert.
Subjects:
City planning.; Zoning.; City planners.
Places:
Annapolis (Md.)--City planning.; Bel Air (Md.)--City planning.; Frederick (Md.)--City planning.; Salisbury (Md.)--City planning.; Burlington (N.C.)--City planning.; Raleigh (N.C.)--City planning.; Martinsburg (W. Va.)--City planning.
Form and Genre Terms:
Maps.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Link to a copy of the printed finding aid. (PDF file) More complete than below.
- Selected list of incoming correspondence (INCOMPLETE)
  - Harland Bartholomew, Mar. 1923 (Box 1)
  - Edward Bassett, Jan. - May 1921 (Box 1)
  - Edward Bassett, June - July 1921 (Box 1)
  - Edward Bassett, Aug. - Sept. 1921 (Box 1)
  - Edward Bassett, Oct. 1921 (Box 1)
  - Edward Bassett, Nov. 1921 (Box 1)
  - Edward Bassett, Dec. 1921 (Box 1)
  - Edward Bassett, Jan. 1922 (Box 1)
  - Edward Bassett, Feb. - May 1922 (Box 1)
  - Edward Bassett, Apr. 1922 (Box 1)
  - Edward Bassett, May 1922 (Box 1)
  - Edward Bassett, Jun 1922 (Box 1)
  - Edward Bassett, Aug. 1922 (Box 1)
  - Edward Bassett, Sept. 1922 (Box 1)
  - Edward Bassett, July 1924 (Box 2)
  - Edward Bassett, Dec. 1925 (Box 2)
  - Edward Bassett, 1941-1946 (Box 2)
  - Russell Black, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Russell Black, Feb. 1935 (Box 2)
  - Arthur Comey, Mar. 1923 (Box 2)
  - Thomas Eldridge, Oct. 1921 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Eldridge, Jan. 1922 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Eldridge, May 1922 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Eldridge, June 1922 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Eldridge, July 1922 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Eldridge, July 1922 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Eldridge, Aug. 1922 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Eldridge, Sept. 1922 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Eldridge, Oct. 1922 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Eldridge, Nov. 1922 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Eldridge, Jan. 1923 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Eldridge, Feb. 1923 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Eldridge, Mar. 1923 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Eldridge, Apr. 1923 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Eldridge, May 1923 (Box 2)
  - Herbert Hoover, May 1925 (Box 2)
  - Henry Hubbard, June 1927 (Box 2)
  - P. C. Painter, July 1922 (Box 1)
  - P. C. Painter, Dec. 1922 (Box 1)
  - P. C. Painter, Oct. 1923 (Box 2)
  - Gustav Requardt, Nov. 1921 (Box 1)
  - Gustav Requardt, Apr. 1922 (Box 1)
  - Gustav Requardt, May 1925 (Box 2)
  - Gustav Requardt, 1947 (Box 2)
  - Lawrence Veiller, Dec. 1921 (Box 1)